Guide to the Frank Alonzo McMullan Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Frank Alonzo McMullan papers
1939-1976
MS 1470
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6
(16 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, topical files, lecture notes, production files and prompt books, typescripts and manuscripts, photographs, costume and set drawings, and printed material documenting Frank McMullan's career in educational and professional theatre.
McMullan, Frank Alonzo, 1907-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of John McMullan, 1987.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series: I. Correspondence and Topical Files, 1945-1966. II. Writings and Lecture Materials, 1931-1976. III. Production Files and Promptbooks, 1933-1967. IV. Photographic Material, 1925-1972.
Scope and Contents
The Frank McMullan Papers contain correspondence, topical files, lecture notes, production files and promptbooks, typescripts and manuscripts, photographs, costume and set drawings, and printed material relating to McMullan's career in educational and professional theatre. The six linear feet of papers are arranged in four series: I. Correspondence and Topical Files, 1945-1966; II. Writings and Lecture Materials, 1931-1976; III. Production Files and Promptbooks, 1933-1967; and IV. Photographic Material, 1925-1972.
The bulk of the CORRESPONDENCE AND TOPICAL FILES (Series I) dates from 1945 to 1966 and relates to McMullan's activities as a theatre educator and director at universities and professional theatres in the United States and abroad. The series includes McMullan's correspondence with Sir Barry Jackson and Leonard Crainford relating to McMullan's production at Stratford-on-Avon, England; correspondence, reports and printed material relating to McMullan's work in Chile, Panama, and the United Arab Republic; personal and work-related correspondence with Allardyce Nicoll, Peter Brook, and John Shubert. No files relating specifically to McMullan's administrative activities at the Yale School of Drama are contained in the papers. The correspondence files of Kingman Brewster, Walter P. Eaton and Allardyce Nicoll provide some insight into that aspect of his career.
Series II, WRITINGS AND LECTURE MATERIALS, dates from 1931 to 1976 and consists of teaching files containing notes and newspaper and magazine clippings which relate to dramatic theorists, playwrights, directors, actors and aspects of theatrical production; manuscripts and typescripts of lectures; notes, clippings and typescripts relating to his book Directing Shakespeare in the Contemporary Theatre. Two files, "Drama 27" and "Play Directing (Course Syllabus)" date from McMullan's graduate study at Yale.
Series III, PRODUCTION FILES AND PROMPTBOOKS, consists of correspondence, notes, clippings, cast lists, set and costume sketches, promptbooks, and programs relating to productions which McMullan directed in educational and professional theatres in the United States, England, Chile, and Panama.
The bulk of PHOTOGRAPHIC MATERIAL (Series IV) consists of photoprints and slides of theatrical productions which were directed by McMullan and others. In addition, there are portrait and candid photoprints of McMullan and photoprints of other individuals, institutions and course-related subjects.
Biographical / Historical
Frank Alonzo McMullan, son of Birda Cornelia Brown McMullan and Wilson Henry McMullan, was born in Jonesboro, Georgia on October 12, 1907. He graduated from Boy's High School, Atlanta, in 1925, received a B.A. from the University of Georgia in 1928, and the LL.B. from the Atlanta Law School in 1930. In 1934 McMullan completed the three year M.F.A. program in drama at Yale, where he studied with George Pierce Baker, Alexander Dean, and Allardyce Nicoll.
From 1934 to 1936, McMullan was on the faculty of Stephens College in Columbia, Missouri, and was co-director of the Stephens College Theater. In 1936 he joined the Yale drama faculty as assistant professor of play production and was acting chairman of the drama department from 1941-1943. From 1943 to 1945 he served in the United States Army where he directed the soldier shows program in New York City for the Special Services division. From 1945 to 1965 McMullan was the head of the directing department at Yale, and until his death was associate professor emeritus of play production at the Yale School of Drama.
McMullan was the director of the University of Vermont School of Drama summer sessions from 1937-1940, and guest directed at numerous professional and educational theatres, including Wellesley (Massachusetts) Playhouse; the University of Arkansas; Ohio State University; University of Connecticut Summer Theatre; Shakespeare Festival (San Diego, California); the Champlain Shakespeare Festival (Burlington, Vermont).
In addition to his work in the United States, McMullan was involved in a number of international educational and professional theatre activities. With his production of Measure for Measure in 1946, McMullan became the first American to direct a Shakespearean play at Stratford-on-Avon, England.
In 1958 McMullan received a Fulbright grant to Chile where he was guest director and lecturer in theatre arts at the Teatro Experimental of the University of Chile and Teatro de Ensayo of Catholic University of Santiago. His direction of the Latin American premiere of Look Homeward, Angel at the Teatro Experimental, and a production of The Taming of the Shrew at the Teatro Ensayo earned him the Chilean national award for directing. As a recipient of a Smith-Mundt grant to Panama in 1959, McMullan assisted in establishing a theatre program and directed The Matchmaker at the University of Panama. In 1962 he organized and headed a performing arts mission to the United Arab Republic on behalf of the United States Department of State and National Guidance of the United Arab Republic.
In 1950 McMullan directed stage and film versions of Telephone Pioneers for the Southern New England Telephone Company, and in 1954 his production of The Merry Wives of Windsor was televised for the NBC series "Omnibus." Between 1956 and 1957 McMullan appeared on his own weekly televison series on station WNHC in New Haven, Connecticut.
McMullan contributed articles to Theatre Arts, Players Magazine and Education Theatre Journal, and authored One World in Drama (1950), Play Interpretation and Direction (1951) (translated into Spanish in 1959), Producing Shakespeare (1954), Shakespeare: Of an Age and for All Time (1954), The Directorial Image (1962), The Director's Handbook (1964), and Directing Shakespeare in the Contemporary Theatre (1974).
McMullan married Elizabeth Eckhard on March 26, 1938 and was the father of two sons, David and John McMullan. Elizabeth McMullan died on December 5, 1977. McMullan subsequently married the former Audrey Tower. Frank McMullan died in Canaan, Connecticut on September 7, 1987.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
College theater; Theater -- Production and direction; Photoprints; Prompt books; Brook, Peter, 1925-; Crainford, Leonard; Jackson, Barry, 1879-1960; McMullan, Frank Alonzo, 1907-; Nicoll, Allardyce, 1894-1976; Yale School of Drama; Yale University. Department of Drama
- CORRESPONDENCE AND TOPICAL FILES, 1931-1976; Series I; 1.75 linear feet (4 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains material arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Actor's Equity, 1964-1965, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bevan, Frank, 1951-1962, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Brewster, Kingman, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brook, Peter, 1946-1947, 1953, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chile, 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 5-8)
  - Chile, 1960-1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    General
    See also: box 16, folder 218
  - Chile, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    See also:box 16, folder 218
  - Chile
    - Printed material, 1950-1959, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Teatro de Ensayo, Teatro Experimental, and others, 1958, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Commendation letters, 1938-1961, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Connecticut, University of (Storrs), 1963-1964, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Crainford, Leonard, 1946 January-July (Box 1, Folder 15)
    See also: box 16, folder 219
  - Crainford, Leonard, 1946, August-December-1948, undated (Box 1, Folder 16-18)
  - Dean, Alexander, 1932, 1936-1938 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - The Directorial Image
    - Comments, 1963-1973, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Permissions, 1961 March-May (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Permissions, 1961 June-Dec, 1962 June (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - The Director's Handbook, 1964, 1969, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Eastern Washington College of Education, 1960-1961, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Eaton, Walter Prichard, 1938, 1940, 1942-1944, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Gilder, Rosamond, 1946-1947, 1958, 1959, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - International Theatre Institute, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Jackson, Sir Barry, 1945-1960, undated (Box 2, Folder 28-30)
  - Keiser, David M., 1961, 1975, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Kelada, Naguib, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Kommisarjevsky, Theodore, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - King, Eleanor, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Light, James, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Lytell, Bert, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Mielziner, Jo, 1946 May 1 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Macalester College, 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    See also: box 16, folder 222
  - Macalester College, 1970-1971, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Meeks, Everett, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Nicoll, Allardyce, 1936-1943, 1945-1966, undated (Box 3, Folder 41-46)
  - North, Alex, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Ohio State University, 1952-1953 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Old Globe Theatre, 1954-1955 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    See also: box 16, folder 223
  - Old Globe Theatre, undated (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Panama, 1958 December-1959 March-Oct, 1960-1961, undated (Box 3, Folder 51-54)
  - Panama (Box 3, Folder 51-54)
  - Panama
    - Printed material (Box 4, Folder 55-56)
  - Patterson, Tom, 1955 December 15 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Plays directed, undated (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1960-1962 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Saint-Denis, Michel, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - San Diego Festival, 1954-1959, undated (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Scofield, Paul (Mrs.), undated (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Shubert, John, 1946-1962 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Slocum, John, 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 64)
    See also: box 12, folder 185
    See also: box 4, folder 66
  - Slocum, John, undated (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - United Arab Republic Mission, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 66)
    See also: box 4, folder 64
  - United Arab Republic Mission, 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - United Arab Republic Mission
    - Printed material, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Vermont, University of, 1939-1941 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - Webster, Margaret, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - Wellesley College, 1947, undated (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - Yale Alumni Convocation, 1963, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - Yale University Library, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Young, Stark, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - Miscellaneous and unidentified, 1968, 1976, undated (Box 4, Folder 75)
- WRITINGS AND LECTURE MATERIAL, 1931-1976; Series II; 1.75 linear feet (4 boxes)
  - Acting, 1947-1949, 1951, 1954, undated (Box 5, Folder 76-77)
  - Anderson, Maxwell, undated (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - Anouilh, Jean, undated (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - Art (general subject), 1956-1957 (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - Audience, 1956-1963, undated (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - Baker, George Pierce, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - Bibliographies, undated (Box 5, Folder 83)
  - Brecht, Bertolt, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 84)
  - Calhoun seminar, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - Chekhov, Anton, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - Costume design, undated (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - Copeau, Jacques, undated (Box 5, Folder 88)
  - Criticism, 1960-1963 (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - Directing Shakespeare in the Contemporary Theatre
    - Notes, 1973-1974, undated (Box 5, Folder 90-91)
    - Clippings, 1938, 1945, 1950-1959, 1961-1976, undated (Box 5, Folder 92-93)
    - "Making Shakespeare Contemporary", undated (Box 5, Folder 94)
    - pp. i-75, undated (Box 5, Folder 95)
    - pp. 76-150, undated (Box 5, Folder 96)
    - pp. 151-225, undated (Box 5, Folder 97)
    - pp. 226-230, undated (Box 5, Folder 98)
    - pp. 301-380, undated (Box 6, Folder 99)
  - Drama 27, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 100)
  - Dramatic values, 1938, 1951-1958, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 101)
  - "Essentials of Play Production", 1961 (Box 6, Folder 102)
  - Expressionism, undated (Box 6, Folder 103)
  - Faust, undated (Box 6, Folder 104)
  - Furniture arrangements and ground plans, undated (Box 6, Folder 105)
  - Giraudoux, Jean, undated (Box 6, Folder 106)
  - Genet, Jean, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 107)
  - Grotowski, Jerzy, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 108)
  - Hamlet, 1957, undated (Box 6, Folder 109)
  - Happenings, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 110)
  - Ibsen, Henrik, 1945, undated (Box 6, Folder 111)
  - Inge, William, undated (Box 6, Folder 112)
  - Interpretation, 1957, 1966, undated (Box 6, Folder 113)
  - Macbeth, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 114)
  - Measure for Measure, 1945, 1956, undated (Box 6, Folder 115)
  - Melodrama, 1954-1957, 1962, 1972, undated (Box 6, Folder 116)
  - Miscellaneous writings, undated (Box 6, Folder 117)
  - New Theatre, 1963-1969, undated (Box 6, Folder 118)
  - O'Casey, Sean, undated (Box 6, Folder 119)
  - Odets, Clifford, undated (Box 6, Folder 120)
  - O'Neill, Eugene, 1953-1957, undated (Box 6, Folder 121)
  - Othello, 1955-1958, undated (Box 6, Folder 122)
  - Pantomime, undated (Box 7, Folder 123)
  - Pictorial dramatization, 1940, 1948, undated (Box 7, Folder 124)
  - Pirandello, Luigi, undated (Box 7, Folder 125)
  - Play Directing (course syllabus), 1931 (Box 7, Folder 126)
  - Play interpretation and direction, 1950, undated (Box 7, Folder 127)
  - Playwriting 1956: U.S. 1918-1956 (Box 7, Folder 128)
  - Playwrights and playwriting, 1939-1940, 1947-1954, undated (Box 7, Folder 129)
  - Repertory theatre, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 130)
  - Reprints, 1936-1963 (Box 7, Folder 131)
  - Resident theatre, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 132)
  - Restoration, 1953, 1948, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 133)
  - Richard II, undated (Box 7, Folder 134)
  - The Rivals, 1961, undated (Box 7, Folder 135)
  - "Scene Design", undated (Box 7, Folder 136-337)
  - "Scene Design", undated (Box 8, Folder 138-339)
  - Scene design and painting, 1931, 1934, 1936, undated (Box 8, Folder 140)
  - Shaw, George. B., undated (Box 8, Folder 141)
  - Sherwood, Robert, undated (Box 8, Folder 142)
  - Strindberg, August, undated (Box 8, Folder 143)
  - Style, 1938, 1946-1966, undated (Box 8, Folder 144-146)
  - The Taming of the Shrew, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 147)
  - The Tempest, undated (Box 8, Folder 148)
  - Theatre of the Absurd, 1962, undated (Box 8, Folder 149)
  - Theatre of Cruelty, 1962, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 150)
  - Timon of Athens, undated (Box 8, Folder 151)
  - Tragedy, 1953, 1955, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 152)
  - Troilus and Cressida, undated (Box 8, Folder 153)
  - Wilder, Thornton, undated (Box 8, Folder 154)
  - Williams, Tennessee, undated (Box 8, Folder 155)
- PRODUCTION FILES AND PROMPTBOOKS, 1933-1967; Series III; 1.25 linear feet (3 boxes)
  This series contains material arranged alphabetically by title of production.
  - Cock-A-Doodle Dandy, 1955, undated (Box 9, Folder 156)
  - Coriolanus, 1955 (Box 9, Folder 157)
  - The Dybbuk, 1933-1935, undated (Box 9, Folder 158-160)
  - Die Feuersbrunst, 1961-1963 (Box 9, Folder 161)
  - Die Beuersbrunst, undated (Box 9, Folder 162)
  - Golden Harvest, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 163)
  - Hamlet, 1941 (Box 9, Folder 164-165)
  - Heartbreak House, 1946 (Box 10, Folder 166)
  - King Lear, 1964, 1965, 1967, undated (Box 10, Folder 167)
    See also: box 16, folder 224
  - Look Homeward Angel ("El angel que nos mira"), 1958 (Box 10, Folder 168-170)
  - Measure for Measure, undated (Box 10, Folder 171)
    See also: box 16, folder 225
  - The Merchant, undated (Box 10, Folder 172)
  - Merry Wives of Windsor, 1954, undated (Box 11, Folder 173-174)
  - Othello, undated (Box 11, Folder 175)
    See also: box 16, folder 226
  - Right You Are…, undated (Box 11, Folder 176)
  - The Rivals, 1961, undated (Box 11, Folder 177)
  - The Taming of the Shrew ("La fierecilla"), [1958] (Box 11, Folder 178-179)
  - Telephone Pioneers of America, 1950 (Box 11, Folder 180)
    See also: box 16, folder 227
  - The Tempest, 1969, undated (Box 11, Folder 181)
    See also: box 16, folder 228
- PHOTOGRAPHIC MATERIAL, 1933-1967; Series IV; 1.5 linear feet (4 boxes)
  This series is arranged in three sections: Photoprints, Oversized photoprints and slides. Within each section the files are arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Photoprints
    - Chile, undated (Box 12, Folder 182)
    - Furniture arrangement, undated (Box 12, Folder 183)
    - Individuals C-S, undated (Box 12, Folder 184)
    - McMullan, Frank, 1962, 1966, 1972, undated (Box 12, Folder 185-186)
    - San Diego National Shakespeare Festival, 1954 (Box 12, Folder 187)
    - Theatre auditoriums
      - Globe, Gutherie, 1963, undated (Box 12, Folder 188)
    - Theatrical productions
      - McMullan productions
        - A-T, 1952, 1954, 1955, undated (Box 12, Folder 189)
        - Ah, Wilderness!, undated (Box 12, Folder 190)
        - Barchester Towers, undated (Box 12, Folder 191)
        - The Barrets of Wimpole Street, undated (Box 12, Folder 192)
        - Cock-A-Doodle Dandy, 1955 (Box 12, Folder 193)
        - The Dybbuk, undated (Box 12, Folder 194)
        - The Importance of Being Earnest, undated (Box 12, Folder 195)
        - King Lear, undated (Box 12, Folder 196)
        - Look Homeward Angel ("El angel que nos mira"), undated (Box 12, Folder 197)
        - Measure for Measure, undated (Box 12, Folder 198)
        - The Merchant, undated (Box 12, Folder 199)
        - The Merry Wives of Windsor, undated (Box 12, Folder 200)
        - Othello, undated (Box 12, Folder 201)
        - Pelleas and Melisande, undated (Box 12, Folder 202)
        - Quality Street, undated (Box 12, Folder 203)
        - The Taming of the Shrew, [1950] (Box 12, Folder 204)
        - Telephone Pioneers of America, undated (Box 12, Folder 205)
        - Three Sisters, undated (Box 12, Folder 206)
        - You and I, undated (Box 12, Folder 207)
      - Productions directed by others A-T, 1925, 1959, 1966, undated (Box 13, Folder 208)
      - Unidentified (Box 13, Folder 209-212)
  - Oversized Photoprints
    - Hamlet, undated (Box 14, Folder 213)
    - The Mighty Ghost O' th' Lower Glunk, 1965 (Box 14, Folder 214)
    - Othello, undated (Box 14, Folder 215)
    - Unidentified productions, undated (Box 14, Folder 216-217)
  - Slides
    - McMullan Productions
      - 4x3¼ and 2x2 formats, undated (Box 15, Folder 216-217)
- FOLIO
  - 1962 calendar with photos of "La Pergola de las flores" (Box 16, Folder 218)
  - Section and ground plan for Shakespeare Memorial Theatre, Stratford-upon-Avon, undated (Box 16, Folder 219)
  - Pomaire, December 1958-February 1959, 1958-1959 (Box 16, Folder 219)
  - Ground plan, section, and stage configuration drawings, Macalester College., undated (Box 16, Folder 222)
  - Ground plan and costume sketch, Old Globe Theatre, San Diego, California, undated (Box 16, Folder 223)
  - Ground plan and set sketch for King Lear, undated (Box 16, Folder 224)
  - Set renderings for Measure for Measure, undated (Box 16, Folder 225)
  - Ground plan for Othello, undated (Box 16, Folder 226)
  - "Photo story" of Telephone Pioneers of America, undated (Box 16, Folder 227)
  - Ground plan for The Tempest, undated (Box 16, Folder 228)